You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that most
chemotherapy drugs
are approved by the FDA
without evidence of benefit
on survival or quality of life?
Here’s our first story.
Over the next few decades,
the number of new cancer cases
will continue to skyrocket. Are
we winning the war on cancer?
Sadly, in general, no,
this despite the introduction of
hundreds of new anticancer drugs.
The war on cancer has been
likened to the war on terror.
No matter how many drone strikes
you do, it's nearly impossible
to kill all the bad guys, and no
matter how precise the bombing,
one must always consider
the collateral damage.
The toxicity from cancer
therapy can be debilitating,
and not just health-wise.
There's also the "financial toxicity."
Patented anticancer drugs
are priced at up to
nearly a thousand dollars a day.
Even with health insurance,
the average cost to patients
for stage IV breast cancer,
for example, can run $190,000.
It's bad enough to be fighting
for your life without bankrupting
your family at the same time –
a problem still common to this day.
Who can forget the apocryphal story
of Walter White, working two jobs
with health insurance and still
could not afford the cancer care?
Now, not everyone is willing
to start their own meth lab,
but many are willing
to go for broke.
A large proportion of cancer
patients reported their willingness
to declare bankruptcy or sell
their homes to pay for treatment.
I mean, look, aren't the high prices
justified if new and innovative
treatments offer significant
benefits to patients?
But you may be shocked
to find out that many
FDA-approved cancer drugs
may lack clinical benefit.
Well, then how did they
become FDA-approved?
Most approvals of cancer
drugs are based on flimsy
or untested surrogate endpoints,
and postmarketing studies rarely
validate the efficacy and safety
of these drugs on patient
centered endpoints.
Let me explain what that means.
New chemo drugs are increasingly
approved just based on
so-called surrogate endpoints, which
means instead of looking at what
we really care about — survival
or quality of life — they approve
drugs based on things like
response rate, tumor shrinkage.
But who cares if a tumor shrinks
if it doesn't actually extend
your quantity or quality of life?
It's kind of counterintuitive,
but just seeing a tumor shrink
on a CT scan or MRI
is not necessarily correlated
with improvements in
survival or symptoms.
In fact, most studies that have
actually followed people out
found low correlations with survival.
The most recent comprehensive
analysis found 90% of studies
of such validation trials found little
correlation with overall survival.
Of 36 new chemo drugs approved
by the FDA based on these kind
of surrogate endpoints,
once they were actually
put to the test
in the real world,
only 1 in 7 was actually
shown to extend life,
and half explicitly flopped,
and the rest remain untested,
revealing that most cancer drug
approvals have not been
shown to, or do not, improve
clinically relevant endpoints.
Exorbitant drug prices are bad
enough for treatments that work,
but charging vulnerable patients
for drugs without evidence that
they actually improve patients
survival and quality of life
is unconscionable.
Why doesn't the FDA require
proof that chemo drugs
actually benefit patients
before approving them?
Drug companies say that requiring
randomized, controlled trials
with meaningful measures
would take too long,
but the study time reduction
using surrogate endpoints
rather than overall survival is
estimated at just 11 months.
So instead of it taking 7.3 years
to come to market on average,
it would take 8.2 years.
Yes, look, we want to get these
drugs out as soon as possible,
but only if they're actually
going to help people.
Do cancer drugs improve
survival or quality of life?
You don't need to know, according
to our broken regulatory system.
And things aren't much
better over in Europe.
A systematic evaluation of
chemo drug approvals showed
that most entered the market
without evidence of benefit
on survival or quality of life.
And even years later, there was
still no conclusive evidence
that these drugs offered any
benefit, and when they did,
the gains were often marginal.
That's why you see editorials
in the Journal of the
National Cancer Institute
referencing Hans Christian Andersen,
the author of the tale of
"The Emperor's New Clothes."
The studies all converge
on a singular conclusion:
only a minority of new cancer drugs
approved by US and European
regulatory authorities in recent years
deliver clinically meaningful benefits
to patients. In fact, some cancer-
related deaths may be hastened,
or even caused, by the toxic
effects of chemotherapy
rather than the cancer itself.
Based on a review of tens of thousands
of cancer patients, in as many as 27%
of cases the cancer treatment itself
caused or hastened death.
Okay, but it might be worth
that risk if the potential benefit
is large enough. And that's
the subject of my next video,
"How Much Does Chemotherapy
Improve Survival?"
Though we often hear new cancer
drugs described as game-changing
breakthroughs, most afford
much more modest benefits.
In my last video, I quoted
a recent editorial in the
Journal of the National Cancer
Institute suggesting that the majority
of new cancer drugs don't deliver
clinically meaningful benefits at all.
At least when they are
later proven to be ineffective,
they're pulled from
the market, right?
No! Even when postmarket studies
show the new drugs to have
no clinically meaningful benefit
compared to not just older drugs
but compared to nothing,
compared to a sugar pill,
most chemo drugs retain FDA
approval and remain on the market,
even at the same ridiculous prices.
In fact, the most expensive drug
they looked at, the one
costing $169,836 a year,
did not improve overall survival at all,
and actually worsened quality of life.
$169,000 just to make you
feel worse with no benefit.
Why pay a penny for a treatment
that doesn't actually help?
And even when they
do improve survival,
what does that actually mean?
Currently, the trend is for Big Pharma
to design large trials that may detect
statistically significant,
but often trivial,
differences in survival endpoints.
For example, check out
this famous trial.
Adding this second drug, erlotinib,
to gemcitabine for advanced
pancreatic cancer significantly
prolonged overall survival.
Yeah, they suffered more side-
effects, but we're not just talking
about tumor shrinkage.
They lived significantly longer.
The placebo group only
lived 5.91 months, whereas
the added drug group survived
all the way to 6.24 months?
Wait a second. They only lived
a third of a month longer?
That's just 10 days.
All the side-effects and expense
for an average of just 10 days?
That's why doctors shouldn't
use the statistical jargon ---
significant improvement in survival ---
while informing patients about
benefits of new treatment.
When patients hear
the word "survival,"
they're not thinking about
a week and a half. If you put
all the new chemo drugs together
approved over the last dozen years,
the average overall survival
benefit is 2.1 months.
Now look, two months is two months,
I don't want to downplay that, but
time and again, surveys have indicated
that patients expect much more.
Incredibly, about three-quarters
of patients with metastatic lung
or colorectal cancer did
not report understanding
that their chemo was not at all
likely to cure their cancer.
I mean, that's the primary treatment,
but the chemo's not curative;
it's just eking out a few
extra weeks or months.
Why weren't the majority
of patients told that?
It's not that they were
being over-optimistic,
explained the researcher. They
were under the mistaken belief
that the treatment offered a chance
of cure when it in fact didn't.
That deprives patients
of the opportunity
to weigh the risks and benefits
and make their own decisions
about their own body.
If you ask cancer patients,
most want at least half a year
to stomach the side-effects,
which suggests that most
cancer patients might not
choose chemotherapy
if they knew how little
they'd actually benefit.
But look, everyone's different.
One patient they interviewed
said living even one week
longer would be worth it;
whereas another said they
wouldn't even want to do chemo
for two extra years of life;
they wouldn't want
anything to interfere with the
quality of the time they had left.
Either way, people deserve
to know the truth.
I find it telling that oncologists
and cancer nurses themselves
express less willingness to
accept intensive chemotherapy,
given the associated toxicities.
Most chemo drugs are cytotoxic,
meaning they work by killing off
cancer cells, but they also
kill off some healthy cells
as collateral damage, which
is why they can damage
our nerves, cause
irreversible heart failure,
slough off the linings of our gut,
or damage your immune system.
Drug companies frequently downplay
the risks, though, for example,
describing this breast cancer drug
as having acceptable side-effect
profiles for most patients, or this
pancreatic cancer drug as having
a manageable and mostly
reversible safety profile.
These were studies published
in top medical journals.
Naturally, readers would take
these statements to be true.
However, if you actually
look at the data,
the number of serious, even life-
threatening side effects was double,
or even five times higher on
the new breast cancer drug.
And the manageable and
mostly reversible side-effects
evidently weren't referring to those
who were killed by the drug.
I like how they even included
like a cheat sheet.
Acceptable toxicity.
Acceptable to whom?
Manageable? Serious events
and deaths can never
be considered manageable.
And feasible? Who would sign
up for a drug whose toxicity
could only be described
as feasible?
Favorable?
Compared to what?
Tolerable? That's for
the patient to decide.
And any drug that kills people
can hardly be considered safe.
Still, patients may very well
consider it worth the risk.
For some cancers, we've
made tremendous strides.
Testicular cancer, for example.
There is greater than a one in
three chance that chemotherapy
could enable you to survive
at least to the five-year mark.
The same with Hodgkin's disease,
a relatively rare form of lymphoma.
But even when researchers
tried to err on the side
of over-estimating the benefit,
for most common cancers —
colon, lung, breast, and prostate —
the chances appear to me
more like 1 or 2 percent.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.